Guide to the Asian Women United Records TAM.320
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Asian Women United Records
1977-2004
1978-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Asian Women United
Wong, Joyce B.
Yee, Evelyn
TAM.320
2 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and 4 flat file folders
Asian Women United (AWU) was a nonprofit organization formed in 1978 that was based in New York City. With a distinctly feminist point of view, the organization sought to support, educate and empower Asian-American women. AWU explored Asian-American women's history and culture and undertook to mobilize community women in the political arena. AWU organized many events including a concert, fundraisers, a mother/daughter social, and various workshops. The organization also participated in International Women's Day, the Women Working Together conference, the Coalition of Asian Women's Groups, and Asian/Pacific American Heritage festivals. The materials in this collection include newsletters, flyers for events hosted by Asian Women United, flyers for events held in coalition with other groups, workshop notes, meeting notes, administrative files, correspondence, newspaper articles, photographs, oversized collages, and two audiotapes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Asian Women United Records and Photographs were gathered during an AWU reunion in 2004, which was hosted by the New York University Asian/Pacific/American Institute and later donated to the Tamiment Library, NYU. Graphics and photographs from this donation were originally separated and established as separate collections, the Asian Women United Photographs (PHOTOS 217) and Asian Women United Graphics (GRAPHICS 023). Collages initially added to Asian Women United Graphics (GRAPHICS 023) were donated by Evelyn Yee in 2004. In 2013, photographs and graphics from these collections were reincorporated into the Asian Women United Records and Photographs (TAM 320). The accession numbers related to these gifts are 2004.004, 2004.006, 2004.014, NPA.2005.241, and NPA.2008.019. And accretion of exhibition panels was received in 2018 with no documentation regarding its provenance; the accession number associated with these materials is 2019.091.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
Asian Women United (AWU) is a New York City based organization, formed in 1978 when the Asian American Women's Caucus split into two groups. As stated in their Statement of Purpose, AWU worked "towards a society free from race and sex discrimination through the development of women as community leaders with an understanding of the Asian woman's issues and concerns." The organization held regular meetings and produced a monthly newsletter entitled In Touch. AWU organized many events including a concert, fundraising events, a mother/daughter social, and various workshops. AWU also participated in International Women's Day, the Women Working Together conference, the Coalition of Asian Women's Groups, and Asian/Pacific American Heritage festivals. Leftist and feminist in its ideological roots, AWU also took official stands on issues such as abortion rights, immigration and refugee policy, discrimination against Asian Americans and distorted images in the mass media, and the Silver Palace Restaurant strike, ILGWU Local 23-25 organizing and other labor struggles.
AWU's first president, Goldie Chu, was active at the local, state and national levels. She was a delegate to the First International Women's Year gathering in Houston, Texas in 1977 and became vice-chair of the National Women's Political Caucus. Other AWU activists included vice-president Angie Cruz, Liz Young, Jacqueline (Jackie) Huey, Joyce Wong, Ginger Chih, Lolita Lacson, Ruby Tsang and Grace Lyu-Volckausen.
In 1982, Wing Productions made a documentary film called, Ourselves, which was both a portrait of key members of AWU and a celebration and examination of several generations of Asian American women's experience. It was shown on PBS stations and in screenings in a number of cities.
In 1986, the organization adopted a less formal structure; in place of regular business meetings it proposed to convene occasional reunions and maintain less formal networks of communication.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, Local 64 Records (WAG 242)
May Chen Papers (WAG 301)
Scope and Contents
The materials in this collection include: the Asian Women United newsletter (In Touch), flyers from events hosted by Asian Women United, flyers from events done in coalition with other groups, workshop notes, meeting notes, administrative files, correspondence, black-and-white and color photographs (ranging in size from 1"x2' to 8"x10") from various events, and newspaper articles. The collection also contains the collected notes that would be put into IKON #9: The AWU Anthology. Additionally, there are select pamphlets about Asian-American and women's issues collected by AWU members, twelve art collages (measuring 18"x24") that address a variety of Asian women's issues, and two audiotape cassettes labeled "Older Women in Community Politics – at Laura's."
Separated Material
One set of the newsletter In Touch was separated into the library catalogue.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Asian American women; Articles.; Asian American women -- Health.; Newsletters.; Asian American women -- Social conditions.; New York (N.Y.).; Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); Chu, Goldie; Asian Women United; Wong, Joyce B.; Yee, Evelyn
- Activities in Coalition with other Women's Groups (including Coalition of Asian Women's Groups), early 1980s; 29545 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Administrative Files, 1979-1980; 29544 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles about AWU (group), 1979-1984; 29543 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Articles about AWU (individual), 1977-1979; 29542 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Articles on Asian Americans, 1980; 29541 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Asian American Legal Issues: Information and Pamphlets, early 1980s; 29540 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Asian American Organizations, Conferences, and Events, 1980-1982; 29539 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Asian American Plays (including David Henry Hwang's "The Dance and the Railroad" and "FOB" and Genny Lim's "Paper Angels"), 1981-1982; 29538 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Asian American Women's Caucus, 1978; 29537 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Asian Pacific American Heritage Festival, 1979-2004; 29536 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Asian/Pacific Women on the Move Conference, 1980; 29535 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Asian Women's Film Fest (International Women's Day): "Mitsuye and Nellie" and "Ourselves", 1982; 29534 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- AWU Journal (proposal and notes), 1978-1982; 29533 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- AWU Timeline (by Goldie Chu), 1977-1986; 29532 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Brochures: Drafts and Final, late 1970s-early 1980s; 29531 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bylaws, 1978; 29530 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Concert: Mellow Yellow Madness (with Sumi Tonooka, Amerasia, and Alex Chin), 1981; 29529 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence: General, 1978-1986; 29528 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence: Regarding Protests and Support (including Silver Palace Restaurant and the Simpson-Mazzoli bill), 1980-1984; 29527 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Election of Officers, 1978; 29526 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Employee Activities Committee of the American Broadcasting Company, 1981-1982; 29525 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Events Hosted by AWU, 1980-1985; 29524 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Exhibition Panels, undated (Flat-file-folder 6, Flat-file-folder 7, Flat-file-folder 8)
- Fifth Anniversary Celebration, 1984-1985; 29523 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- General Meeting: Notes, Minutes, and Attendance, 1980-1984; 29522 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Goldie Chu (AWU's first president): Notes, 1985-1986; 29521 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- IKON #9: The AWU Anthology: Notes, 1988; 29520 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- International Women's Day and International Working Women's Day, 1981-1984; 29519 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Letterhead, undated; 29518 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mailing Lists, c. 1980s; 29517 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Membership Lists, 1979-1981; 29516 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Membership Questionnaire, 1981; 29515 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Newsletter: In Touch, 1978-1985; 29514 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Notes by AWU Members, c. 1980s; 29513 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ourselves(film): Publicity and Comment, 1982; 29512 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photo Album #1, late 1970s-1980s; 464636 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
- Photo Album #1 - Photocopies (in original order), late 1970s-1980s; 464637 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Photo Album #2 - Prints and Photocopies, late 1970s-1980s; 464638 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Reaching the Young Women of Chinatown: A Youth Diversion Program Specifically for Recent Immigrants, 1979-1981; 29511 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Remarks Prepared for the Hearings of the Select Commission on Immigration and Refugee Policy, 1980; 29510 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Retreat, Annual, 1979-1986; 29509 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Reunion, Sep 25, 2004; 29508 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Women Against Pornography Notes, 1982-1982; 29507 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Women's Rights Pamphlets and Flyers, early 1980s; 29506 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Workshops, 1978; 29505 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Audiotapes and Access Compact Disks: "Older Women in Community Politics – at Laura's" (2 cassettes and 2 CDs), 1984; 29503 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Art Collages, circa 1982; 464639 (Flat-file-folder 1 Left)